Guide to the Vintage Equipment Collection RG.011
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Vintage Equipment Collection
Early-mid 20th century
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
RG.011
11
12 Cubic Feet 13 items
The items in this collection relate to the fields of electrical and civil engineering, as well as supplemental equipment, and were used by engineers in the early to mid 20th century.
Biographical / Historical
The items in this collection were transferred to the Poly Archives by various university departments. The most prominently represented departments include Civil Engineering and Electrical Engineering.
Scope and Contents
Equipment in this collection includes items civil and electrical engineers would have used in the early to mid 20th century. Surveying equipment, such as a theodolite and transit, as well as electrical engineering instruments, such as a decade capacitor, decade resistor, potentiometer, and volt meter are included. The equipment ranges in date from the early to mid 20th century.
Arrangement
Items in this collection are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is currently on display in the Bern Dibner Reading Room of the Bern Dibner Library of Science & Technology.
Please contact the archives to view items in this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials.
Civil engineering; Surveying; Electrical engineering; Engineering; Kodak camera; Equipment and supplies; Radio -- Equipment and supplies; Brownie camera
- Series I: Vintage Equipment
  - Book Binding Stapler: Acme Stapling Co., Camden, NJ, undated; 5963 (Object 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    This heavy-duty stapler was used to bind the pages of manuals and textbooks.
  - Current Transformer: Astra Corporation, Quincy, MA, undated; 5964 (Object 2)
    A transformer is a piece of equipment used by electrical engineers to test electrical current. If the current in the circuit is too high for a direct measurement, the current transformer is used to produce a reduced current proportional to the current in the circuit.
  - Decade Capacitor, Series 1575: Cornell-Dubilier Electronics Inc., Plainfield, NJ, circa 1940; 5965 (Object 3)
    A decade capacitor is used for testing and calibration of electrical equipment
  - Decade Condenser Type 219-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950; 5966 (Object 4)
    The condenser was used when a resistor of unknown or precise value is needed. Condensers are now referred to as capacitors.
  - Decade Resistor Type 1432-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950; 5967 (Object 5)
    The resistor box contains resistors of many values with mechanical switches to allow precision switching from one value to another. This configuration offers a convenient way of quickly changing resistance in a laboratory setting.
  - Electrical Cables: Consolidated Edison Co., New York, NY, undated; 5968; These cables were removed from the display when it was discovered they were leaking a viscous fluid. They were bagged and returned to the archives. (Object 6)
    NYU-Poly and Con Edison have a long-standing relationship of mutual research and support. Con Ed was one of NYU-Poly's first neighbors in the new MetroTech Center complex. These electrical cables and components were donated from Con Ed to NYU-Poly.
    Note on cable reads, "Piece of cable installed in Morgan Stanley building, that failed."
  - Gauge: Airco, New York, NY, undated; 5969 (Object 7)
    This gauge was used to measure the pressure of various gases.
  - Hawkeye Brownie Camera: Eastman Kodak, Rochester, NY, circa 1950; 5970 (Object 8)
    The Hawkeye was one of the most popular Brownie cameras made. It was cheap, easy to use, and disassembled easily for cleaning: the perfect camera to take into the field.
  - Potentiometer: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, circa 1950; 5971 (Object 9)
    This instrument is a voltage divider used for measuring electric potential.
  - Theodolite: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated; 5972 (Object 10)
    The theodolite is an optical surveying instrument used by civil engineers to measure angles in vertical and horizontal planes. When the telescope is pointed at an object, the angle of orientation can be measured with precision.
  - Transit: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated; 5973 (Object 11)
    A transit is a type of theodolite. Rather than being closed, the transit has an open design where measurements are made by reading verniers on metal circles. This transit, produced by the Buff & Buff Company, is often referred to as a Buffmaster Transit.
    On Loan
    On loan to President Andrew Hamilton's Office, 4 February 2016
  - Volt Meter, Model 377: Simpson Electrical Co., Chicago, IL, circa 1950; 5974 (Object 12)
    This instrument is used to measure the electrical potential difference between two points in an electric circuit.
  - Wheatstone Bridge: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, undated; 5975 (Object 13)
    The Wheatstone bridge is a type of potentiometer that measures electrical resistance by balancing two legs of a bridge circuit.
- Series II: Frank Baranowski (NYU Heights) Thesis and Engineering Equipment, circa 1930-1965
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These items were donated to the Poly Archives by Frank Baranowski's daughter, Susan Baranowski in February 2021. Accession 20-001.
  Arrangement
  This donation is housed in two boxes and arranged into two sub-series: Sub-series A: Engineering Equipment, circa 1930-1965 and Sub-series B: Academia, 1954. Items are listed alphabetically.
  Frank Baranowksi was born on November 1, 1921 in Bayonne, New Jersey and received a BS in Chemical Engineering from New York University Heights on June 5, 1943 and an MS from the University of Tennessee. Baranowski was a World War II vet and an engineer on the Manhattan Project. He passed away in Williamsburg, Virginia on August 30, 2017.
  Scope and Contents
  These items mainly include engineering equipment such as slide rules, drafting tools, and scales from the 1930s-1960s. They are located in bay 29 shelf 4C.
  - Sub-series A: Engineering Equipment, circa 1930-1965
    - Clay Adams Co. Scale with Weights in Wooden Box, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Dietzgen Drafting Instruments (11 piece) in Black Case, circa 1930 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - Engineering Instruments Inc. 10-inch Slide Rule, undated (Box 1, Item 3)
    - Keuffel & Esser Beginner's Slide Rule, undated (Box 1, Item 4)
    - Keuffel & Esser Slide Rule and Leather Case with Instruction Booklet, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 5)
    - Lutz Architect's Triangular Ruler, undated (Box 1, Item 6)
    - Sterling Slide Rule and Black Plastic Case, 1965 (Box 1, Item 7)
    - The Frederick Post Company Small Slide Rule and Leather Case, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Sub-series B: Academia, 1954-06
    - Beginnings of Tau Beta Pi by Edwin S. Stackhouse, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - New York University Copy of June 5, 1943 Commencement, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Thesis Inserts and USB Drive Content Note, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Thesis: "Steady State Forced Heat Convection in Non-Compressible Fluids in Laminar Flow Through Circular Pipes," June 1954, 1954-06 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - USB Drive Containing Thesis Files, undated (Box 2, Item 2)